<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A precious and most divine letter from that famous and ever to be renowned Earl of Essex, (father to the now Lord Generall his excellence) to the Earl of South-Hampton, in the latter time of Queen Elizabeths reigne. Printed according to order.</title>
            <author>Essex, Robert Devereux, Earl of, 1566-1601.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1643</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 10 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 6 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A84096</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing E3308</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E250_1</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R187964</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99871148</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99871148</idno>
            <idno type="VID">159066</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A84096)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 159066)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 43:E250[1])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A precious and most divine letter from that famous and ever to be renowned Earl of Essex, (father to the now Lord Generall his excellence) to the Earl of South-Hampton, in the latter time of Queen Elizabeths reigne. Printed according to order.</title>
                  <author>Essex, Robert Devereux, Earl of, 1566-1601.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 3, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1643]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imprint from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "London. Aug: 14. 1643".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Southampton, Henry Wriothesley, --  Earl of, 1573-1624 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Christian life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Conversion --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:159066:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 37 -->
            <pb facs="tcp:159066:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 38 -->
            <pb facs="tcp:159066:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 38 -->
            <pb facs="tcp:159066:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 39 -->
            <p>A PRECIOUS <hi>And moſt Divine</hi> LETTER FROM THAT FAMOUS, AND Ever to be renowned Earl of ESSEX, (Father to the now Lord Generall his Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence) to the Earl of SOUTH-HAMPTON, in the latter time of Queen ELIZA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>BETHS Reigne.</p>
            <p>Printed according to Order.</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>printer's or publisher's device</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>
               <add>London Aug: 14. 1643</add>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:159066:4"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 40 -->
            <pb facs="tcp:159066:4"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 40 -->
            <head>To the <hi>READER.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His Letter, many Yeares ſince received from the hands of a moſt Honourable Perſon, eminent in the Court in thoſe <hi>Elizean</hi> dayes, (when Honour crowned <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>irtue, and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>irtue was the glory of the Times) I have long ſtored up for my owne private, as a Gem and Treaſure ineſtimable.</p>
            <p>Earthly Treaſures waſte, but Heavenly increaſe by Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation! Beſides, I feare (with the Lepers of Old) I doe not well long to conceale, what all that read will judge to be a Common Treaſure. What the Author was for Heigth and Greatneſſe all know; What for Grace and Goodneſſe (though Envy or Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance, have as it were Conſpired to Vaile over his Orient Luſtre) thou mayeſt take ſome ſcantling of by this.</p>
            <p>His Magnanimity and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>alour the World knew, as farre as <hi>Hercules</hi> his Pillars, and the utmoſt Extent of the <hi>Heſperian</hi> Pride. His Humility and Plaine-heartednes (which heightned Him above all his Honours) thoſe that knew him were not ignorant of.</p>
            <p>That Noble <hi>Heroe</hi> yet lives in the true Succeſſor of Honour and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>irtue, our Noble <hi>GENERALL.</hi>
            </p>
            <q xml:lang="lat">(Neque degeneres pariunt Aquilae Columbas.)</q>
            <lb/>
            <p>His incorrupted Fidelity, Valour, and Wiſedonme, are above the reach of Ignorant or Envious Malignants.</p>
            <p>His immovable Reſolution (ever, and of late expreſt) to deny his Honour, his owne Wiſedome, yea his life for the Common Safety, ſhines ſo bright in the Eyes of all Judicious, that nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb facs="tcp:159066:5"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 41 -->the malicious fomentings of Malignant Spirits, nor the weake Clamors of impatient Ignorance, nor the Neceſſity of Gods moſt holy Providence, (exerciſing his Excellency and the Kingdome, I hope for good) I ſay that none, nor all of theſe, can juſtly cloud and Eclipſe his Shine and Luſtre.</p>
            <p>There is nothing within the Circumference of Politicall and prudentiall Arts, that hath more uncertaine and various E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vents then that of Warre: <hi>Eventus Belli incertus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The protracting lengthning, ſhortning, lies in the hand of a higher Excellency, even onely his, in whoſe hand is our Way and Breath, as <hi>Daniel</hi> told <hi>Belſhazzar.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Greateſt and beſt Commanders that ever the World yet ſaw, muſt remember, in whoſe hand is their VVay and Breath, and both they and all Men muſt with Patience ſee (for oft it comes to paſſe) both Moneths, and Summers ſpend beyond their Thoughts, Deſires, Endeavours, and yet no Blemiſh to their VViſdome, Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour, Fidelity, or Vigilancy.</p>
            <p>He that is the God of Peace mercifully ſhew us the Paths of it, even of that Peace, which no Man can give nor take from us.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:159066:5"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 41 -->
            <head>A LETTER FROM That famous, and ever to be renowned Earle of ESSEX, to the Earl of <hi>South-hampton,</hi> in the lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter time of Queen ELIZABETHS Reigne.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My Lord,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S neither nature nor cuſtome ever made me a man of complement, ſo now I ſhall have leſſe will than ever for to uſe ſuch Ceremonies, when I have left with <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tha</hi> to be <hi>ſolicitus circa multa,</hi> and believe with <hi>Mary, unum ſufficit:</hi> but it is no com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plement or Ceremony, but a reall and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary duty that one friend oweth to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in abſence &amp; eſpecially at their ſeave taking, when in mans reaſon many acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents may keep them long divided, or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps barre them ever meeting till they meet in another world; for then ſhall I thinke that my friend, whoſe ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, whoſe Perſon, and whoſe fortune is deare unto me, ſhall proſper and be happy where ever he goes, and what ever he takes in hand when he is in the favour of that God, under whoſe protection there is onely ſafety, and in whoſe ſervice there is onely true happineſſe to be found. What I thinke of your naturall gifts or abilities in this age, or in this State, to give glory to God, and to winne honour to your ſelfe, if you imploy the Talents you have received to their beſt uſe, I will not now tell you, it ſufficeth, that when I was fartheſt of all times from diſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling, I ſpake truly, and have witnes enough: but theſe things only I will put your Lordſhips in mind of.</p>
            <p>Firſt, that you have nothing that you have not received.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:159066:6"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 42 -->
Secondly, that you poſſeſſe them not as Lord over them, but as an accomptant for them.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, If you imploy them to ſerve this world, or your own world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly delights, (which the Prince of this world will ſeek to entertain you with) it is ingratitude, it is injuſtice, yea it is perfidious treacherie. For what would you thinke of ſuch a ſervant of yours, that ſhould convert your goods committed to his charge, to the advantage or ſervice of your greateſt enemy; &amp; what do you leſſe than this with God, ſince you have all from him, and know that the world, and Prince thereof, are at a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuall enmity with him? and therefore if ever the admonition of your trueſt friend ſhall be heard by you or if your Countrey which you may ſerve in ſo great and many things, be deare unto you; If your God, whom you muſt (if you deale truly with your ſelfe) acknowledge to be powerfull over all, and juſt in all be feared by you; yea if you be dear unto your ſelfe and preferre an everlaſting happines before a pleaſant dreame, which you muſt ſhortly awake out of, and then repent in the bitternes of your ſoul; if any of theſe things be regarded by you, then I ſay, call your ſelfe to account for what is paſt, cancell all the leagues you have made without the warrant of a religious conſcience, make a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute Covenant with your God, to ſerve him with all your natural and ſpirituall, inward and outward gifts and abilities, and then he that is faithfull (and cannot lie) hath promiſed to honour them that honour him; He will give you that inward peace of Soul, and true joy of heart, which till you have you ſhall never reſt, and which when you have, you ſhall never be ſhaken, and which you can never attaine to any other way than this that I have ſhewed you.</p>
            <p>I know your Lordſhip may ſay to your ſelfe, and object to me, this is but a vapor of melancholie and the ſtile of a Priſoner, and that I was far enough from it, when I lived in the world as you doe now, and may be ſo again when my fetters be taken from me. I anſwer, though your Lordſhip ſhould thinke ſo, yet cannot I diſtruſt the goodneſſe of my God that his mercy will fail me or his grace forſakeme; I have ſo deeply ingaged my ſelfe, that I ſhould be one of the moſt miſerable Apoſtates that ever was, I have ſo avowed my profeſsion and called ſo many from time to time to witnes it, and to be watchmen over me, that I ſhould be the holloweſt hypocrite that ever was borne: But though I ſhould periſh in my owne ſin, and draw upon my ſelfe my own damnation, ſhould not you take hold of the grace and mercy in God which is offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed unto you; and make your profit of my fearful and wretched example?
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:159066:6"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 42 -->I was longer a ſlave and ſervant to the world and the corruptions of it. then you have bin, and therefore could hardlyer be drawn from it. I had many calls, and anſwered ſome of them ſlowly; thinking a ſoft pace faſt enough to come to Chriſt and my ſelfe forward enough when I ſaw the end of my journy, though I arrived not at it, and therefore I have been by Gods providence violently pul'd, hal'd, and drag'd to the Marriage Feaſt as the world hath ſeen. It was juſt with God to afflict me in this world that he might give me joy in another. I had too much knowledge when I performed too little obedience, and was therefore to be beaten with double ſtripes: God grant your Lordſhip may feel the comfort I now enjoy in my unfaigned converſion, but that you never feele the torments I have ſuffered for my too long delaying it; I had none but Divines to call upon me, to whom I ſaid, if my ambition could have entred into their narrow hearts, they would not have bin ſo humble; or if my delights had bin taſted by them, they could not have been ſo preciſe: but your Lordſhip hath one to call upon you, that knowes what it is you now injoy, &amp; what the greateſt fruit and end is of all the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentments that this world can afford. Thinke therefore deare Earl, that I have ſtaked &amp; bounded all the waies of pleaſure to you, &amp; left them as Sea markes for you to keep the Channell of religious virtue; for, ſhut your eyes never ſo long they muſt be open at laſt, and then you muſt ſay with me, there is no peace to the wicked. I will make a Covenant with my Soul, not to ſuffer my eyes to ſleep in the night, nor my thoughts to attend the firſt buſines of the day, till I have prayed to my God, that your Lordſhip may believe and make profit of this plaine, but faithfull admonition; and then I know your Countrey and friends ſhall be happy in you, and Your ſelf ſucceſſefull in all you take in hand; which ſhall be an unſpeakeable comfort to</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Lordſhips Couſin and true friend, whom no world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly cauſe can divide from you <hi>ESSEX.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
